Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by Mark Severin
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates by Mark Severin
1922-1963
BKP 125
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
This collection includes bookplates and other graphic works by Mark Severin (1906-1987), a Belgian artist and graphic designer.
Severin, Mark F.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011, it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Mark Fernand Severin (1906-1987) was a Belgian artist and graphic designer, active mostly in England. He designed hundreds of bookplates, including many erotic ex-libris designs, as well as postage stamps, book illustrations, advertising posters, and other graphic works.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the following materials: bookplates designed by Mark Severin (1906-1987) for a variety of patrons; bookplates designed for Severin by other artists; other graphic works by Severin, including several Christmas and New Year's greeting cards; and correspondence and ephemera by Severin or otherwise related to the collection, though unattached to specific bookplates.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates by Severin. II. Bookplates by Other Artists for Severin. III. Other Works by Severin. IV. Correspondence and Ephemera.
Bookplates; Bookplates; Severin, Mark F.
- Bookplates by M. Severin, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by patron name. Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains primarily bookplates for individuals, although a few institutional bookplates are also present. Multiple designs for the same patron are filed together, and most files are accompanied by typed notes, which identify artist's proofs and varying states, provide additional context from Severin's letters, etc.
  - Anonymous [erotic plate], undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anonymous [title vignette in a book about bookplates], undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anonymous [group of nature lovers], undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Abra, [1944]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AK, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amici Bibliothecae Universitatis Bruxellensis, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The folder also includes an original pencil sketch for this bookplate design.
  - City of Antwerp, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - L. Asperslag, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Giorgio Balbi, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Banque Nationale de Belgique, 1942; 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - E. Barnes, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bastin [Castelli Spyensis], undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jacques Beaupain, 1958 undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    This folder contains one armorial bookplate; four bookplates featuring a sailing ship superimposed with a woman's face (varying states); and a letter written by Jacques Beaupain to Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt, dated February 27, 1958.
  - M. Beernaerts, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Louis van der Berghe, undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    This folder contains a pencil-and-ink drawing for a maritime bookplate design as well as a two prints and a watercolor-and-pencil original sketch for a bookplate design featuring an okapi.
  - Berqueman, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Eric Vansittart Bowater, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - British Museum Natural History Department, 1963; 11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    This folder contains ten small pencil sketches, lettered b through k, and a letter concerning the design written by Severin to Mr. Rowlands, dated March 3, 1963.
  - W. D. Britt, undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carlo Bronne, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Y. de Brouwer, Duc in Attum, undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - M. Brumwell, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lucy de Bruyne, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Louis Burgers, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Georgette Callebaut, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Valentin Le Campion, undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mary Churchill, [1945]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - C. K., undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Arlette de Clerq, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - J. & S. de Clerq, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - A. Le Clerq, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - A. Clifford, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - S. Cockerell, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Albert Collart, [1960], undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Rika Collart, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - J. M. Collet, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cooreman, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    This folder contains a page from Severin's sketchbook that shows seven preliminary designs (six pencil, one watercolor) for the Cooreman bookplate, including an original sketch for the final design.
  - Lou Cosyn, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Maurice Crick, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Andre & Elaine Danis, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - F. Delacre, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - J & M Delwart, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - A. & J. Devos, undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Dr. Devisvanden Eeckhoudt, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - H. Dirkx, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    This folder contains variations on an HD monogram design as well as a pictorial bookplate featuring a variety of bird species; Dirkx was an avid bird watcher.
  - D. M., undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - G. S. Dorman, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Dott-Nerone Santa Giuliana, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Helene Dubois, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - F. Douglas, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - H. Florin de Duikingberg, undated; 8 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - J. Dumont, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Editiones des Artistes, 1943 undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Eggermont, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - T. S. Eliot, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - F. & B. Fenton, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Fruiter's Company, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Hugh and Joan Flower, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - D. Flower, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - M. P. J. Fontaines, E.C., undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - J. Francois, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Jose Francois, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - G.H.B. [C.H.B.], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - John Gartner, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Lea Geerlandt, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Girl Stella of Penzance, 1936; 1 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    This folder contains a bookplate designed for the library aboard the yacht, "Girl Stella."
  - W. J. Gotz, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Henri Goyens, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - C. Grasemann, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Basil V. R. Greatrex, undated; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Václav Grégr, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Guédroïtz, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - M. Hardy, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - George Maclean and Margaret Dawson Hellyer, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Jacques Henricot, undated; 4 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - J. B. Hepburn, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - E. D'Hooghe, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Max Horn, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - I. M. A. Irchonwelz, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Institute Pour La Recherche Scientifique En Afrique Centrale, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - J. B., undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - H. F. Jackson, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - P. Janssens, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - S. Jasinski, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Jesus College, Cambridge, undated; 4 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Allan Keen, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - G. V. Lamboitte, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - L. Leplae, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - LePrince & Irene LePrince, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - F. LePrince Jungbluth, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - P. E. Lévy, undated; 8 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Claire and Francis Leys, circa 1922; 2 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Franz Leytens, undated; 5 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Jean Lummerzheim, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Fr. Luyckx, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Gima Gianni Mantero, 1947 undated; 6 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Paul Marteau, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Frank Martin, undated; 9 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - G. Martin, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - R. Maton, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Marcel de Merre, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    This folder contains a super ex-libris design that is a gold stamp on brown leather.
  - A. W. Miller, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - James Moran, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Georges Neelmans, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Johannes Van Noten, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - René Pechère, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - A. Pelckmans, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Bryan S. Potter, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Kristen Rasmussen, undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Emmerick Reumert, [1953]; 5 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Claude Rolin, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - A. Rousseau, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Anthony Picton Saunders-Davies, 1933; 1 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - A. Saverys, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - John Schwencke, undated; 5 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Lawrence H. Seccombe, 1937 undated; 7 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Lawrence H. Seccombe, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 116a)
    Includes engraved woodblock for bee-keeping bookplate of Lawrence H. Seccombe.
  - Severin's Early Ex-Libris, undated; 11 items (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Mark F. Severin, 1941 undated; 25 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    This folder also contains bookplates designed by Mark Severin for his wife, Nina.
  - Simonson Libraire Bruxelles, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 119)
    This is a design for a bookseller's label.
  - J. Frederick Smith, [1951] undated; 5 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Société Générale de Belgique, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 121)
    This folder contains two artist's proofs as well as a pencil drawing of the larger version of this armorial ex-libris design.
  - A. R. Solly, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - O. Solvay, [1958]; 2 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Southern Railway Staff Training College, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Fernand Spaak, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - André de Staercke, undated; 8 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - J. van der Stricht, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - J. Theunis, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - A. C. Ward, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Hilda Wiener, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 130)
    This folder only contains a photographic reproduction of Severin's ex-libris design for Mrs. Wiener.
  - Barclay and Isobel Wiggins, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Lilian & John Wilkinson, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - W. W. Winkworth, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - M. & C. Wolfers, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - E. Young, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - W. Zwiers, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 136)
- Bookplates by Other Artists for Severin, Series II
  Arranged according to the accompanying checklist.
  This series contains bookplates designed for Severin by other artists. It includes works by: B. Bramanti, T. Buckland Wright, Cecil Keeling, A. Decaris, Ernst Gohlert, Anton Vermeyten, Valentin Le Campion, Ruda Gajdos, Italo Zetti, Lucharsky, Frank Martin, and G. Gandaen.
  - Bookplates by Other Artists for Severin, [1941] 1963 undated; 31 (Box 3, Folder 137)
- Other Works by Severin, Series III
  This series contains other graphic work by Severin, including a birth announcement; an MS monogram design; a map of Uccle, Belgium; and several Christmas and New Year's greeting cards.
  - Other Work by Severin, 1936-1937 1958-1962 undated; 33 (Box 3, Folder 138)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, Series IV
  This series contains eight letters from Severin to Irene D. Andrews Pace, dating from 1947 to 1959, and six letters from Severin to Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt, dating from 1954 to 1962. In addition, the series also contains exchange cards and various checklists of Severin's work (including lists generated and annotated by Severin himself).
  - Severin Correspondence and Ephemera, 1947-1962 undated (Box 3, Folder 139)